{"tossups": [{"question": "This man criticized the use of wet nurses and advocated for breastfeeding by mothers in a 1752 thesis titled <em>Nutrix Noverca</em>. This man had to flee Hamburg after angering its mayor when he declared that a seven-headed hydra corpse he possessed was fake. Peter Forssk\u00e5l, who died while on an expedition in Yemen, was among the seventeen dedicated \u201capostles\u201d of this man. The author of <em>Systema Naturae</em>, for ten points, what Swedish naturalist is often called the \u201cfather of modern taxonomy\"?", "answer": "Carl <b><u>Linnaeus</u></b> (or Carolus <b><u>Linnaeus</u></b>; accept Carolus a <b><u>Linn\u00e9</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "King Pyrrhus of Epirus used the excuse of enrolling his heirs in this program to justify an invasion of the Peloponesse. A trip to Crete inspired the semi-mythical figure Lycurgus [[lye-KUR-guss]] to introduce this system, including the use of a common mess hall and a restriction on bathing. This system, which was often led by more experienced men known as <em>paidonomoi</em>, was chronicled by the Athenian Xenophon, who put his own sons into this program while serving as a mercenary. The youth of Sparta were subjected to, for ten points, what twenty year program of militaristic training?", "answer": "<b><u>Agoge</u></b> [[ah-GOH-gay]] (or <b><u>Ag\u014dg\u0101</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This act was meant to pressure another country into repealing its Orders in Council. This act was opposed by Secretary of the Treasury Albert Gallatin, who proposed Macon\u2019s Bill Number One as an alternative. This act was passed in response to the <em>Chesapeake-Leopard</em> Affair and was represented in a comic depicting a snapping turtle biting the backside of a man who complains, \u201cThis cursed Ograbme.\" For ten points, name this act, promoted by Thomas Jefferson, that blocked foreign trade in response to British naval impressment.", "answer": "<b><u>Embargo</u></b> Act of 1807", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man deployed diplomat Afanasiy Pushkin to negotiate an \"Eternal Peace\" with the delegates of Charles IX [[the ninth]]. Dionysus the Grammarian attempted to unseat this man from power by convincing one ruler to divorce this counselor's sister, Irina. This man, Feodor Nikitich Romanov, and Vasili Shuiski served on the advisory council which effectively ran the nation for the son of Ivan the Terrible, Feodor I. The Time of Troubles began following the death of, for ten points, which non-Rurikid tsar?", "answer": "<b><u>Boris</u><u>Godunov</u></b> (or <b><u>Bor\u00eds</u></b> Fyodorovich <b><u>Godun\u00f3v</u></b>; accept either underlined portion)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Elders from this group read scripture underneath multi-colored umbrellas on a holiday known as Sigd, or Mehlella. In one country, the \"Blood Bank Affair\" banned these people from giving blood out of fear of HIV. Operations Joshua and Solomon airlifted this group to one country, at the time led by Yitzhak Shamir. Members of this group who convert to Christianity to seek a better life are called Falash Mura. Referred to as \"exiles\" in Amharic, for ten points, what minority religious community has largely emigrated to Israel from Africa?", "answer": "<b><u>Ethiopia</u></b>n <b><u>Jew</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Beta Israel</u></b>; accept <b><u>Falash Mura</u></b> or <b><u>Falasha</u></b>s before \"Falash\"; prompt on \"Jews\")", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "One theory claims the bones of this figure were stolen by several Yale alumni led by Prescott Bush while serving as Army volunteers at Ft. Sill. The distribution of <em>mezcal</em> was used by Mexican soldiers to massacre this chief's soldiers at Casas Grandes in Chihuahua. Multiple escape attempts by this figure were followed by his formal surrender to Nelson A. Miles in Arizona. A military leader of the <em>Bedonkohe</em> Apache was, for ten points, what man whose name is shouted by paratroopers when jumping out of planes?", "answer": "<b><u>Geronimo</u></b> (or <b><u>Goyaal\u00e9</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Eric Nilles and Anil Menon conducted a 2020 study of thousands of employees at this company, revealing that COVID-19 infection rates were lower in those who already contracted the disease. The Technical University of Munich's engineering team won all four iterations of the Hyperloop competition hosted by this company. Amateur astronomer Bill Gray revealed that, in early 2022, the remnants of this company's Falcon 9 were slated to collide with the moon. The colonization of Mars is the end goal held by, for ten points, what extra-terrestrial exploration company founded by Elon Musk?", "answer": "<b><u>SpaceX</u></b> (or <b><u>Space Ex</u></b>ploration Technologies Corporation)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This researcher studied the cultures he labelled \"Totemic societies,\" including the Australian Aborigines and the Pueblo, in his work <em>The Elementary Forms of the Religious</em> <em>Life</em>. This man considered the trial of Socrates a \"necessary release of social tensions\" and \"a useful prelude to reforms\" in Athens in <em>The Rules of the Sociological Method</em>. The concept of <em>anomie</em> is used to illustrate reasons one may commit the title action in, for ten points, which French sociologist's work <em>Suicide</em>?", "answer": "Emile <b><u>Durkheim</u></b> (or David Emile <b><u>Durkheim</u></b>)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Sociology"}, {"question": "While serving in the Army Air Corps, this composer was commissioned to write his <em>Cello Concerto</em> for Raya Garbousova [[gahr-boh-SOH-vah]] by the Boston Symphony Orchestra. Olin Downes faced intense criticism after a <em>New York Times</em> review praising a string orchestra work by this composer, taken from a movement of his <em>String Quartet in B</em> <em>minor</em>. That piece by this composer was played during the announcements of the deaths of Franklin D. Roosevelt and John F. Kennedy. Arturo Toscanini premiered a piece by, for ten points, what American composer of <em>Adagio for Strings</em>?", "answer": "Samuel <b><u>Barber</u></b> (or Samuel Osborne <b><u>Barber</u></b> II)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "The book <em>The Man Who Never Was</em> details an effort during this campaign that involved Ewen Montagu\u2019s goading of one side to divert troops to another country. During this campaign, Operation Avalanche targeted the western part of its central region. Harold Alexander led an Army Group that oversaw this campaign which forced Adolf Hitler to abandon a planned Kursk Offensive and reinforce its central area. During this campaign, Generals Patton and Montgomery engaged in a race to see who could first reach Messina. For ten points, name this Allied campaign to capture an Italian island.", "answer": "Allied <b><u>Invasion</u></b> of <b><u>Sicily</u></b> (prompt on partial answers; accept synonyms for <b><u>Invasion</u></b> such as <b><u>Attack</u></b>; accept <b><u>Sicilia</u></b> in place of <b><u>Sicily</u></b>; accept Operation <b><u>Husky</u></b>; accept Operation <b><u>Avalanche</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This event began the day after a group of Greek immigrants celebrated Orthodox Easter. Cripple Creek veteran John Chase commanded one group of armed men during this event. Camp leader Louis Tikas was violently beaten during this event by Karl Linderfelt before being shot in the back and left near the train tracks for three days. Mother Jones organized the United Mine Workers strike against John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Colorado Fuel and Iron Company that precipitated, for ten points, what 1914 massacre of coal miners?", "answer": "<b><u>Ludlow</u></b> Massacre", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man served as the chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster as a member of the Labour Party. This man came into conflict with communist counter-protestors under Phil Piratin and Metropolitan Police officers led by Philip Game during a \u201cbattle\u201d that led to the passage of the 1936 Public Order Act. That act outlawed the wearing of political uniforms in public demonstrations and responded to this non-Italian man\u2019s \"Blackshirts.\" For ten points, name this leader of the British Union of Fascists who led a march that culminated in the Battle of Cable Street.", "answer": "Oswald <b><u>Mosley</u></b> (or Sir Oswald Ernald <b><u>Mosley</u></b>, 6th Baronet)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This country's 1948 Civil War was sparked by the assassination of People's Vanguard leader Mora Valverde and the overthrow of Teodoro Picado. Quakers from Alabama who failed to become conscientious objectors moved to this country's town of Monteverde, which contains a cloud forest. This country's president, Jose Figueres Ferrer, abolished the army as a precaution against the militarism seen in other Central American countries. Formerly split between New Granada and New Spain, for ten points, what is this country between Nicaragua and Panama?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Costa Rica</u></b> (or Republica de <b><u>Costa Rica</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Following the Battle of Alnwick, this ruler incorporated the counties of Westmoreland and Cumberland at the expense of the Scottish monarch, Malcolm III. Nobleman Walter Tirel was accused of killing this king with an arrow during a hunting trip, an assassination that may have been ordered by this king's sibling, Henry Beauclerc [[boh-KLEHRK]]. For ten points, name this Anglo-Norman king and son of William the Conqueror, nicknamed for his red hair.", "answer": "<b><u>William II</u></b> (or <b><u>William Rufus</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The book <em>What the Eyes Don\u2019t See</em> chronicles this event, during which Doctor Mona Hanna-Attisha founded an organization to deal with its effects. An outbreak of Legionnaires\u2019 Disease coincided with this event, which led to charges being sought against Rick Snyder. Leaching resulting from a lack of corrosion inhibitors partly caused this event, which occurred after a source of its central good was no longer treated at a sewage plant. For ten points, name this 2014-2019 public health crisis that affected a Michigan city.", "answer": "<b><u>Flint Water</u></b> Crisis (accept descriptive answers of the <b><u>water</u></b> crisis in <b><u>Flint</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "The term \u201credlegs\u201d referred to impoverished inhabitants of several islands in this body of water. The preacher Paul Bogle led a protest among inhabitants of an island in this body of water during the Morant Bay Rebellion. A Welshman who became lieutenant governor of an island in this body of water was Henry Morgan, who clashed with that island\u2019s <em>maroon</em> population. Sugar plantations were built on islands in this body of water\u2019s Lesser Antilles. For ten points, name this formerly pirate-infested sea containing Puerto Rico and Jamaica.", "answer": "<b><u>Caribbean</u></b> Sea (accept Mar <b><u>Caribe</u></b>; or Mer des <b><u>Cara\u00efbes</u></b>; or <b><u>Kiaribiyan</u></b> Sii; or Laman <b><u>Karibe</u></b>; or <b><u>Caraibische</u></b> Zee)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "At an event in this city, Pete Seeger offered to use an ax to stop a performance because of the acoustics. In this city, Paul Gonsalves performed a saxophone solo for 27 choruses during a performance of Duke Ellington's \"Diminuendo and Crescendo in Blue.\" The playing of \"Maggie's Farm\" opened a performance in this city, in which a folk singer shocked a crowd by, for the first time in his career, playing an electric guitar on stage. For ten points, Bob Dylan \"went electric\" at a jazz festival in which Rhode Island city?", "answer": "<b><u>Newport</u></b> (accept <b><u>Newport</u></b> Folk Festival; or <b><u>Newport</u></b> Jazz Festival)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Jazz"}, {}, {"question": "While serving as chancellor of New York, Nathan Sanford ran in this presidential election year, winning 30 vice-presidential votes. The \u201cWyoming Letters\u201d promoted one candidate in this election year whom the <em>Smithsonian</em> claimed was not \u201creared on sweetmeats from the tables of kings and princes.\u201d The Nashville Junto aimed to portray the losing candidate in this election year as the \u201cHero of New Orleans.\u201d A defeat for a man given the moniker \u201cOld Hickory\u201d, for ten points, what was this year in which the election was decided by a \u201ccorrupt bargain\u201d which favored John Quincy Adams?", "answer": "United States Presidential Election of <b><u>1824</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>The leader Treniota led a group from this country called the Samogitians</u></b> <b><u>against the Livonian Order at the Battle of Durbe. Duke Daumantas assassinated the</u></b> <b><u>first Grand Duke of this country, who possibly renounced Christianity and approved</u></b> <b><u>the construction of the Klaipeda Castle. Mindaugas (+)</u> led this country, as did a national hero who ended a civil war by making peace with Jogaila. This country, led by Vytautas [[vee-\"TAO\"-tahs]], was later linked to (*) </b>Poland in a namesake Commonwealth. For ten points, name this country in which Stephen Bathory established Vilnius University.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Lithuania</u></b> (or <b><u>Lietuvos</u></b> Respublika; or <b><u>Lietuva</u></b>; accept Grand Duchy of <b><u>Lithuania</u></b>; accept Polish-<b><u>Lithuania</u></b>n Commonwealth)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Paracelsus [[pah-rah-SEL-sus]] believed this phenomenon occurred due to</u></b> <b><u>\"overheated blood,\" while local burghers attempted to end this craze by clearing the</u></b> <b><u>open-air grain market for two weeks. One theory concerning this phenomenon claims</u></b> <b><u>German peasants (+)</u> were exposed to the psychoactive </b><em><b>ergot</b></em><b> [[ER-got]] fungi occasionally found in rye bread. People afflicted with this phenomenon were brought to the grotto of St. Vitus. (*) </b>16th century Strasbourg was struck with, for ten points, what \"Plague\" during which people gyrated uncontrollably?", "answer": "<b><u>Dancing</u></b> Plague (or <b><u>Dancing</u></b> Mania; accept St. <b><u>Vitus's Dance</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A co-founder of this organization, along with his brother, Francis, oversaw</u></b> <em><b><u>Galaxy Magazine</u></b></em><b><u> which employed Mark Twain. That man was William Conant Church,</u></b> <b><u>who co-founded this organization with an author of a popular manual (+)</u> its members often read. George Wingate was an early leader of this organization, the national profile of which was raised when Ambrose Burnside became president. (*) </b>For ten points, name this organization that promoted breech-loading varieties of its namesake weapon and was once led by actor Charlton Heston.", "answer": "<b><u>National Rifle Association</u></b> (accept <b><u>NRA</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>American missionary Daniel Vrooman created a 19th century map of this city</u></b> <b><u>which included an accurate depiction of its mercantile ghetto, the Thirteen Factories.</u></b> <b><u>Members of a nationalist student organization led by Huang (+)</u> Xing [[ZHING]] were massacred during this city's Yellow Flower Mound Uprising, a part of the larger Xinhai [[ZHIHN-HYE]] Revolution. This city names a \"System\" instituted by Qing [[CHING]] China which forced all western trade to be concentrated along the Pearl River. (*) </b>Canton is an alternative name for, for ten points, what capital of Guangdong?", "answer": "<b><u>Guangzhou</u></b> (accept <b><u>Canton</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This event is described as \"dark as the world of man, black as our loss / Blind</u></b> <b><u>as the nineteen hundred and forty nails / Upon the cross\" in Edith Sitwell's poem</u></b> <b><u>\"Still Falls the Rain.\" After Maurice Bendrix's home is destroyed in this event, Sarah</u></b> <b><u>Miles (+)</u> breaks off her affair in Graham Greene's novel </b><em><b>The End of the Affair</b></em><b>. A poem about this historical event ends, \"After the first death, there is no other\" and features a speaker who will not mourn the \"death, by fire, (*) </b>of a child.\" For ten points, name this often memorialized German bombing campaign against Britain during World War Two.", "answer": "The <b><u>Blitz</u></b> (accept the Battle of <b><u>Britain</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man was criticized for taking an elephant-hunting trip to Botswana paid</u></b> <b><u>for by Mohamed Eyad Kayali. This man's mistress, Corinna zu Sayn-Wittgenstein-Sayn</u></b> <b><u>admitted to the press that this man had received millions of dollars in kickbacks from</u></b> <b><u>interests building the Haramain (+)</u> high-speed railway. In 2014, this leader was succeeded by his son (*) </b>Felipe after abdicating the throne. Living in self-exile since 2020 due to corrupt business dealings in Saudi Arabia, for ten points, who is this former king of Spain?", "answer": "<b><u>Juan Carlos</u></b> I (or <b><u>Juan Carlos</u></b> Alfonso V\u00edctor Mar\u00eda de Borb\u00f3n y Borb\u00f3n-Dos Sicilias)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>William F. Packer defeated this man in one election, preventing him from</u></b> <b><u>becoming the first Republican governor of Pennsylvania. This politician stated that</u></b> <b><u>\"Slavery has within itself the seeds of its own destruction\" in a speech given before</u></b> <b><u>running for Speaker (+)</u> of the House in 1849 as a Free Soil candidate. Jacob Brinkerhoff and Gideon Welles assisted in drafting a bill named for this man that arose from fears that Polk was promoting (*) </b>Southern interests through war. For ten points, give this namesake of an unpassed bill that would have banned slavery in territory gained during the Mexican-American War.", "answer": "David <b><u>Wilmot</u></b> (accept <b><u>Wilmot</u></b> Proviso)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This writer was inspired by a 1934 coal miner uprising led by Belarmino</u></b> <b><u>Tom\u00e1s to pen the play</u> </b><em><b><u>R\u00e9volte dans les Asturies</u></b></em><b><u>. Jean-Paul Sartre and this writer</u></b> <b><u>contributed to the paper \"Combat,\" which (+)</u> served as counter-propaganda to Nazi disinformation in occupied France. The Daniel Defoe account </b><em><b>Journal of a Plague Year </b></em><b>inspired the tale of Dr. Bernard Rieux [[ROO]], who tries to cure the title pestilence in this author's </b><em><b>The Plague</b></em><b>. Ethnic tensions in his homeland of (*) </b>Algeria inspired, for ten points, which author's <em>The Stranger</em>?", "answer": "Albert <b><u>Camus</u></b> [[kah-MOO]]", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "<b><u>A fugitive named Kerry Dee Ketchum was caught by authorities after posing</u></b> <b><u>under the name \u201cPatrick Quin\u201d on one of these programs. A 1994 Robert Redford film</u></b> <b><u>portrayed a controversy on one of these programs, which involved Herb Stempel and</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> Charles Van Doren on the show </b><em><b>Twenty-One</b></em><b>. Another one of these programs hosted a 2011 exhibition match between an IBM supercomputer named Watson and two of the show\u2019s greatest champions, Brad (*) </b>Rutter and Ken Jennings. For ten points, what type of television program includes the shows <em>Wheel of Fortune</em> and <em>Jeopardy!</em>?", "answer": "<b><u>Game</u></b> shows (accept <b><u>Quiz</u></b> shows)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}], "bonuses": []}